Marilynn Gelfman Karp Collection of Ephemera PR 279
New-York Historical Society
- Series III. Trade and Trading Cards, circa 1875-1915, 1964
  - Redeemable Baking Soda Trade Cards, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 66)
    Arm & Hammer Baking Soda, founded in 1846, began inserting trade cards within their packaging in 1888 and remained a popular household collectable for five decades. Issued in 2 sizes (1 7/8" x 3" and 1 1/2" x 2 1/4"), they are especially notable for their sophisticated aesthetics and early promotion of wildlife conservation. Among those included in this collection, are examples from the earliest issued series "Beautiful Birds of America."
  - Blatz Chewing Gum "Screen Stars" (full set), circa 1920s (Offsite-box 5, Folder 67)
  - John F. Kennedy Trading Cards, 1964 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 209)
- Series IV. Blotters, circa 1890-1955
  With the introduction of the first practical fountain pens during the 1880s, card blotters were a popular and practical novelty giveaway item by many businesses. Once as ubiquitous as today's business cards, advertising blotters stood ever-ready by the home phone, or on the desk, as a reminder of goods and services offered. Their designs (which often featured monthly calendars) ranged from the traditional promotion of retailers, banks, and insurance companies, to risque pinup art. By the 1950s, the increasing popularity of ballpoint pens led to a gradual end to this advertising trend.
  - Food, circa 1890s-1940s (Offsite-box 5, Folder 68)
  - Products/Services, circa 1890s-1940s (Offsite-box 5, Folder 69)
  - Products/Services, circa 1890s-1940s (Offsite-box 5, Folder 70)
  - Products/Services, circa 1890s-1940s (Offsite-box 5, Folder 71)
  - Products/Services, circa 1890s-1940s
  - Pinup Girls, circa 1940s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 73)
  - Pinup Girls, circa 1940s-1950s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 74)
- Series V. Cigarette Silks, circa 1900-1915
  A variation of the cigarette card, cigarette silks served as promotional giveaways included in cigarette packaging of the early 20th century. Highly collectable in their time, they were printed in various thematic series (birds, butterflies, actresses, etc.) of 25 or more, instigating repeat purchases of the same brand. Cigarette silks had particular marketing appeal to women, who would often incorporate them into decorative household items, such as quilts, pillows, and table coverings.
  - Birds, circa 1900-1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 75)
  - Chickens, circa 1910-1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 76)
  - Actresses, circa 1900-1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 77)
  - Porcelain (Set of 15), circa 1900-1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 78)
  - Various, circa 1900-1915 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 79)
- Series VI. Needle Books, circa 1870-1955
  Commercial needle books (or packets) began to be manufactured in the early 19th century, in the Redditch District of central England. By the mid 19th century, needle-making machinery had fully mechanized production, and needle book graphics became increasingly elaborate. Like trade cards, they served as portable forms of advertising for various goods and services, often emphasizing domestic and travel-related imagery.
  - Needle Books, circa 1870-1925 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 80)
  - Needle Books, circa 1910s-1950s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 83)
  - Needle Books, circa 1920s-1950s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 81)
  - Needle Books, circa 1920s-1950s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 82)
- Series VII. Labels (paper and tin), circa 1875-1955
  Product Labels: While the practice of utilizing printed labels is as old as printing itself, modern package design did not begin to evolve until after the Civil War when advancements in printing, paper production and chromolithography made the affordable mass production of elaborate and colorful designs possible. By 1900, chromolithography would reach its zenith, prompting some to call the latter half of the 19th century the period of "chromo-civilization." Included here are various examples of how printed labels were utilized for packaging, identification, and instructive purposes, displaying a fascinating compendium of design styles and influences reflective of their eras.
  Hatbox Labels: The modern hatbox (a derivative of the Victorian bandbox) was a frequent item found among the possessions of both men and women well into the mid 20th century, when the wearing of hats was customary for all occasions. As a valued accessory, it was a standard practice for hats to be sold with hatboxes for their protection. These boxes (commonly made of sturdy pasteboard and decorative paper), came adorned with an elegant label displaying the name of the manufacturer or department store where purchased, along with a convenient carrying strap. In this way, the box transcended its practicality by serving as a portable form of status and advertising for both the owner and the retailer. Perhaps because of their usefulness as physical containers, attractive packaging, and the sentiment attached to them as objects of value, many hatboxes have survived among families over several generations and continue to be utilized and collected for a variety of purposes.
  Luggage Labels: Luggage labels, with their elegant graphics featuring exotic locals, luxury modes of transportation, and grand hotels, bear witness to the "Golden Age of Travel," a period which spanned the late 19th century to the outbreak of World War II. Affixed to luggage by railroad companies, steamships, hotels, and resorts, they provided the practical means of identifying luggage destination, but also served as romantic advertisements for the destinations themselves. For the traveler, such labels were a sign of personality, taste and status, and over the course of years, their accumulation provided an autobiographical history of places visited, hotels stayed in, and transportation used. A remnant of past places and times, they beautifully evoke the spirit of this bygone era.
  Please Remit: The economic prosperity of the 1950s, spurred by the growth of commercial advertising and the introduction of the modern credit card, gave way to unprecedented consumer optimism and spending, as more and more Americans embraced the ease and convenience of "putting it on plastic" as a way to pay for purchases. For many collection agencies, a useful aid in collecting debts was the "Please Remit" notice, inserted into billing envelopes as a way to cajole payments from debtors after two or three months of unpaid bills. Today these "friendly reminders" provide a nostalgic look at the mores and manners of an earlier time.
  Product Labels
  While the practice of utilizing printed labels is as old as printing itself, modern package design did not begin to evolve until after the Civil War when advancements in printing, paper production and chromolithography made the affordable mass production of elaborate and colorful designs possible. By 1900, chromolithography would reach its zenith, prompting some to call the latter half of the nineteenth century the period of "chromo-civilization." Included here are various examples of how printed labels were utilized for packaging, identification, and instructive purposes, displaying a fascinating compendium of design styles and influences reflective of their eras.
  - Product Labels -- Grooming, circa 1900-1935 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 84)
  - Product Labels -- Food and Beverage; Household (includes booklet of baking labels), circa 1900s-1940s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 85)
  - Product Labels -- Olive Oil (printed tin), circa 1875-1955 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 86)
  - Product Labels -- RX, circa 1920s-1950s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 87)
  - Hatbox Labels, circa 1900s-1950s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 88, Folder 89, Folder 90)
  - See The Pyramids (luggage labels), circa 1900s-1940s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 91)
  - Wire It (telegraph poster stamps, labels and postcards), circa 1930s-1950s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 92)
  - Please Remit, undated (Offsite-box 7, Folder 93)
- Series VIII. Pictorial Glassine Snack Bags, circa 1935-1955
  Glassine paper, a smooth and semitransparent glazed, greaseproof and leak resistant product, was developed in 1905 and soon became adapted as an ideal packaging material for fast foods and snacks. In 1908, the Milwaukee Printing Company developed a method of printing on glassine paper, and these printed bags and wrappers (often with lively typeface and engaging graphics) became a standard feature at American concession stands, for such fare as hamburgers, peanuts, and ice cream bars.
  - Pictorial Glassine Snack Bags, circa 1930s-1950s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 94)
- Series IX. Hairnets in Packaging, circa 1920s-1967
  Hairnets (once known as "cauls," or "snoods") have been used in various forms since ancient times, serving both utilitarian and decorative purposes. While initially constructed of materials such as silk and ribbon, the first commercial reference to hairnets made of human hair appeared in July, 1863, as an editorial feature in Peterson's Magazine (Vol. XLIV, No. 1). By 1914, the hairnet was a common hair accessory for women, and over the ensuing years became increasingly promoted for use in the nursing and food service professions. The emancipated bobbed hairstyles of the 1920s brought a temporary decline in the use of hairnets. Their popularity was revived by World War II, a period which saw the return of longer hairstyles and the entrance of women into the industrial workforce. Further refinements to hairnet manufacturing included the introduction of Du Pont's multifilament nylon yarn in 1940, offering unprecedented resiliency and wear.
  - Hairnets in Packaging, circa 1910s-1960s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 95)
  - Hairnets in Packaging, circa 1940s-1960s (Offsite-box 7, Folder 96)
- Series X. Decals, circa 1930-1955
  The invention of transfer decals, attributed to the French engraver Simon François Ravenet (a process he coined "decalquer" or "to copy by tracing"), originated in England in the mid 18th century, initially as a method by which to transfer decorative designs to pottery using engraved copper plates and tissue paper. Over the course of the 19th century, a variety of advancements in technology such as lithography, the paper making machine, and the invention of duplex paper, made the affordable mass production of decals possible. The introduction of silk screen printing in the early 20th century allowed a top-coat or cover-coat of lacquer to be added to the decal design (so-called water-mount decals) which could be transferred when wet.
  Introduced to the United States by approximately 1865, the demand for decals reached its zenith in the 1870s resulting in what came to be called "decalcomania." Decals remain popular today offering an inexpensive way to decorate and enhance a variety of objects and surfaces.
  - Star Cal -- Favorite Stars, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 97)
  - Children/Nursery, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 98)
  - Seashore, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 99)
  - Mermaids and Swans, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 100)
  - Birds, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 101)
  - Flamingos, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 102)
  - Flowers and Fruit, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 103)
  - Dishes, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 104)
  - Servers, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 105)
  - Pinup Art, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 106)
  - Holland, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 107)
  - Mexico, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 108)
  - Travel Souvenirs, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 109)
  - Signs, circa 1940-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 110)
  - Various, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 111)
  - Glassine Decal Packaging, circa 1930-1955 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 112)
  - Cockamamies and skin-transfers [tattoos], circa 1940's - 1950's (Offsite-box 18, Folder 210)
  - Impko miniature decals, circa 1950's - 1960's (Offsite-box 20, Box 18A, Folder 216)
- Series XI. World War II Ephemera (various formats), circa 1942-1945
  See also
  Greeting Cards, Postcards, and Sheet Music
  Ration Books and OPA Points: In August, 1941, President D. Roosevelt created the Office of Price Administration (OPA) in order to regulate both the purchase and cost of consumer goods during a period of severely limited imports and wartime shortages. By the spring of 1942, the first of 4 series of War Ration Books and stamps or "points" were issued to each American family. The program served as a way to promote the "fair share of certain goods made short by war," and carefully control the amount of foods, necessities, and luxuries any one person could buy. For the average citizen, such daily sacrifice represented a challenging but essential and patriotic contribution to the American war effort.
  Army Navy Hit Kit Songs: In 1941, a Sub-Committee on Music was established by the Joint Army and Navy Committee on Welfare and Recreation to advise the Army, Navy, and Marine Corps on matters relating to musical activities and entertainment for servicemen both in and outside military camps and reservations from 1941-1946. A popular part of this program began in 1943 with the monthly issuing of pamphlet-size songbooks called "Army Navy Hit Kits" containing the lyrics and music of popular songs of the period, including both "Hit Parade" and patriotic-themed songs. Important morale boosters during the war years, Hit Kit pamphlets, issued by the War Department's Special Services Division, were available only to military personnel and not for sale to the general public.
  U.S. War Department Photographs: 47 linen-backed captioned training photographs (from a pre-World War II US War Department Federal Binder) by US Army Signal Corps of US Field Artillery Pack Units (4th, 97th, 98th and 99th Battalions), showing training for combat at US Bases in 1941-1942.
  Smilin' Jack Bubblegum Cards: Full, uncut set of 128 Smilin' Jack bubblegum cards with "Buy War Bonds & Stamps for Victory" on verso. This set is based on the 1943 movie serial, and the aviation comic strip (also 1943).
  Posters: During World War II, American government officials successfully harnessed the use of propaganda through the poster medium in an effort to mobilize the nation towards a united and urgent support for the war effort and American victory. A major function of the Office of War Information (OWI), created in 1942, was responsibility for controlling the content and imagery of war posters, and ensuring their monthly distribution and promotion across the nation. Drawing from the powerful and persuasive stylistic conventions of the advertising industry, American home front posters embraced American consciousness with themes that emphasized the nature of the enemy, the nature of the allies, the need to work, fight, and sacrifice, and the need to protect the principles of American freedom.
  See also: Greeting Cards, Postcards, Sheet Music, and Posters
  Ration Books and OPA Points: In August, 1941, President D. Roosevelt created the Office Price Administration (O.P.A.) in order to regulate both the purchase and cost of consumer goods during a period of severely limited imports and wartime shortages. By the spring of 1942, the first of 4 series of War Ration Books and stamps or "points" were issued to each American family. The program served as a way to promote the "fair share of certain goods made short by war," and carefully control the amount of foods, necessities, and luxuries any one person could buy. For the average citizen, such daily sacrifice represented a challenging but essential and patriotic contribution to the American war effort.
  Army Navy Hit Kit Songs: In 1941, a Sub-committee on Music was established by the Joint Army and Navy Committee on Welfare and Recreation to advise the Army, Navy, and Marine Corps on matters relating to musical activities and entertainment for servicemen both in and outside military camps and reservations from 1941-1946. A popular part of this program began in 1943 with the monthly issuing of pamphlet-size songbooks called "Army Hit Kits" containing the lyrics and music of popular songs of the period, including both "Hit Parade" and patriotic-themed songs. Important moral boosters during the war years, Hit Kit pamphlets, issued by the War Department's Special Services Division, were available only to military personnel and not for sale to the general public.
  Photographs: 47 linen-backed captioned training photographs (from a pre-WWII US War Department Federal Binder), by US Army Signal Corps of US Field Artillery Pack Units (4th, 97th, 98th and 99th Battalions), showing training for combat at US Bases in 1941-1942.
  Smilin' Jack Bubblegum Cards: Full, uncut set of 121 Smilin' Jack bubble gum cards, Buy War Bonds & Stamps for Victory, based on the 1943 movie serial, and the aviation comic strip (also 1943).
  - Ration Books And OPA Points, circa 1940s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 113)
  - Victory Stationary, circa 1940s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 114)
  - Army Navy Hit Kit Songs, 1944 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 115)
  - Wartime Maps, circa 1940s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 116)
  - Weapons for Victory Flyers, circa 1940s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 117)
  - Smilin' Jack Bubblegum Cards (full set), 1943 (Oversize Flat File, Folder 117a)
  - World War II - Various, circa 1940s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 118)
  - U.S. War Department Photographs, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 119)
  - U.S. War Department Photographs, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 120)
  - U.S. War Department Photographs, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 121)
  - U.S. War Department Photographs, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 122)
  - Post World War II (American market) -- American Japanese Holiday Coloring and Talking Book, circa 1950s-1960s (Offsite-box 9, Folder 123)
  - Posters, 1942-1943 (Oversize Flat File, Folder 197)
  - Field manual for first aid; War Injuries pamphlets, 1943-1944 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 211)
  - Fighting Yanks Around the World by Thomas Penfield, 1943-1944 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 212)
  - Low on the War, A Cartoon Commentary of the Years 1939-1941 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 213)
- Series XII. Miscellaneous Paper Items, undated
  - Cigar Pouch [depicts woman dumping chamber bowl out of window onto gentleman below], circa 1880 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 215)
  - Lost Pet Notices, undated (Offsite-box 9, Folder 124)
- Series XIII. Annual Linoleum Pattern Books, 1921-1952
  The invention of linoleum, a name coined from the Latin words "linum" (flax) and "oleum" (oil), was patented in England in 1860 by Frederik Walton, a rubber manufacturer, who founded the first linoleum company in 1864. By the end of the decade, linoleum was introduced to the United States, with the first US-based production beginning in 1874. Affordable, attractive, and resilient, as well as naturally bactericidal, flame and scratch-resistant, linoleum became a favorite surface material in American homes and hospitals, offering vibrant colors and myriad of creative patterns that included imitation marble, stone, mosaics, and faux carpeting designs. Lighter gauge linoleum was also created for use on walls, including Lincrusta (Lincrusta-Walton), Linowall (Armstrong), and Sealex Wall-Covering and Congowall (Congoleum).
  By the 1930s, Armstrong was the largest manufacturer of linoleum in the America, offering consumers hundreds of patterns from which to choose. Linoleum manufacturers published "pattern books" to advertise their designs, and offered homemakers free booklets with illustrated advice for incorporating linoleum into their interior decorating schemes.
  In the years following World War II, the introduction of cheaper PVC (vinyl) flooring brought the use of linoleum into sharp decline. Today, patterned linoleum is enjoying renewed popularity as a "green" recyclable flooring alternative that is environmentally friendly and biodegradable.
  - Armstrong, 1923-1928 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 125)
  - Armstrong, 1921-1930 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 126)
  - Armstrong, 1930-1931 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 127)
  - Armstrong, 1936 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 128)
  - Armstrong, 1937 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 129)
  - Armstrong, 1944 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 130)
  - Armstrong, 1949 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 131)
  - Armstrong, 1952 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 132)
  - Armstrong, 1953 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 133)
  - Certain-teed, 1928 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 134)
  - Sloane, 1928 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 135)
  - Sloane, 1952 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 136)
  - Congoleum Nairn, 1924-1943 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 137)
  - Pabco, 1941-1949 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 138)
  - Bird, 1941-1946 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 139)
  - Floor and Wall Coverings: Prepared Especially for Home Study, 1952 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 140)
  - Photographs of Window Displays, circa 1920s (Offsite-box 11, Folder 141)
  - Armstrong- Linoleum Frame (Offsite-box 11.A)
- Series XIV. Magazines, 1938-1960
  - Subseries XIV.1: Hairdressing Magazines, 1938-1950
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1938 December (Offsite-box 11, Folder 142)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1939 January (Sections I & II) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 143)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1939 May (Section II) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 144)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1939 June (Offsite-box 11, Folder 145)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1939 October (Offsite-box 11, Folder 146)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1939 December (Offsite-box 11, Folder 147)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1940 April (Offsite-box 12, Folder 148)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1940 July (Offsite-box 12, Folder 149)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1940 August (Offsite-box 12, Folder 150)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1940 November (Offsite-box 12, Folder 151)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1941 November (Offsite-box 12, Folder 152)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1942 December (Offsite-box 12, Folder 153)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1943 January (Section I) (Offsite-box 12, Folder 154)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1943 December (Offsite-box 12, Folder 155)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1945 December (Offsite-box 12, Folder 156)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1946 January (Offsite-box 12, Folder 157)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1946 April (Offsite-box 12, Folder 158)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1946 December (Offsite-box 12, Folder 159)
    - Modern Beauty Shop, 1947 January (Offsite-box 12, Folder 160)
    - The American Hairdresser, 1939 June (Offsite-box 12, Folder 161)
    - The American Hairdresser, 1939 December (Offsite-box 12, Folder 162)
    - The American Hairdresser, 1940 December (Offsite-box 13, Folder 163)
    - The American Hairdresser, 1941 December (Offsite-box 13, Folder 164)
    - The American Hairdresser, 1942 December (Offsite-box 13, Folder 165)
    - The American Hairdresser, 1946 January (Offsite-box 13, Folder 166)
    - The American Hairdresser, 1946 December (Offsite-box 13, Folder 167)
    - The American Hairdresser, 1948 December (Offsite-box 13, Folder 168)
    - The American Hairdresser, 1949 December (Offsite-box 13, Folder 169)
    - The American Hairdresser, 1950 January (Offsite-box 13, Folder 170)
  - Subseries XIV.2: Nudist magazines, 1947-1960
    - Sunshine & Health, 1947 May, 1959 April, 1960 December (Offsite-box 19, Folder 214)
    - Sunbathing for Health, 1948 June, 1951 July (Offsite-box 19, Folder 214)
    - Natural Herald, 1950 December - 1951 March, 1953 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 214)
    - Health & Efficiency, 1951 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 214)
    - Nudisme et Beaute, 1951 September - October (Offsite-box 19, Folder 214)
    - Tidlosa, 1957 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 214)
    - Sun and Health, 1960 April (Offsite-box 19, Folder 214)
    - Nudism explained!, undated (Offsite-box 19, Folder 214)
- Series XV. Sheet Music, 1842-1948